Guide to the Jason Altmire Congressional Papers, 2006-2012 AIS.2013.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Jason Altmire Congressional Papers
2006-2012
2007-2012
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Altmire, Jason
AIS.2013.01
209 folders
The Jason Altmire Congressional Papers document the Western Pennsylvania politician's career in the United States House of Representatives. Rep. Altmire, a Democrat, was elected in 2006 to represent the Pennsylvania 4th congressional district (PA-04), which at the time included parts of Allegheny, Beaver, Butler, Lawrence, Mercer, and Westmoreland counties. During his tenure, Rep. Altmire successfully introduced 29 pieces of legislation which became law, spoke over 200 times on the House floor, served on several brief occassions as the Speaker Pro Tempore, cast 4,732 consecutive votes, and returned nearly $1 million in unspent funds by the end of his third term. Serving on the House Committees for Education and Labor, Small Business, and Transportation and Infrastructure, he was an advocate for military veterans and their families, health care reform, investment in small business and energy, and government reform. Rep. Altmire gained notoriety for his opposition as a Democrat to the 2010 health care reform law known as the Affordable Care Act.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following 16 series, structured as a file directory and is available through the Archives & Special Collections "Digital Reading Room." Researchers will need to request access to the "Digital Reading Room" by contacting the Archives & Special Collections by sending a message through Ask-An-Archivist (https://www.library.pitt.edu/ask-archivist).
Series I. Administrative Files
Series II. Congressional Correspondence
Series III. Congressional Delegation Files
Series IV. Constituent Communications
Series V. Thank You Cards and Letters
Series VI. Invitations
Series VII. Issue Files
Series VIII. Legislative Files
Series IX. Personal Files
Series X. Press Files
Series XI. Speech Files
Series XII. State and District Files
Series XIII. Moving Images Files
Series XIV. Photographic Files
Series XV. Recorded Audio and Sound Files
Series XVI. "Citizens for Altmire" Campaign Files
Biography
Jason Altmire was born March 7, 1968 in Kittanning, Pennsylvania, and grew up in a single-parent household. He set school records in track and field and became an all-star wide-receiver on his high school football team before matriculating at Florida State University and joining the FSU Seminoles football team. He graduated in 1990 with a Bachelor of Science in Political Science and began working on Pete Peterson's successful 1990 campaign for Florida's 2nd Congressional District. From 1990-1996, Altmire worked in Rep. Peterson's Capitol Hill office as a legislative assistant specializing in domestic policy issues, particularly healthcare. In 1996, Altmire took a position with the Federation of American Hospitals, eventually earning a Master's of Health Administration from George Washington University in 1998.
Altmire returned to Western Pennsylvania and worked for the University of Pittsburgh Medical Center (UPMC) from 1998 to 2005, eventually becoming Vice President of Government Relations and Community Health Services. He was first elected to represent constituents from Pennsylvania's 4th Congressional District in the House of Representatives in 2006, and won re-election twice, in 2008 and 2010. During his tenure in office, Rep. Altmire served on the Education & Workforce Committee and Transportation & Infrastructure Committee. He was distinguished by his moderate voting record and staunch advocacy for military veterans and their families, health care reform, small businesses, and higher education investment. While in Congress, he introduced 49 bills and amendments that passed through the House, 29 of which became law. His bill to modernize the American Legion was cosponsored by 432 Representatives, the most recorded in U.S. History. During his first two terms, he did not miss a single vote, casting 4,732 consecutive votes, and returned more than one million dollars in unspent funds over the course of his tenure. He was also involved directly, along with then-Pennsylvania Governor Ed Rendell, in the high profile airlift of two Pennsylvania constituents and 54 orphans from the Bresma Orphanage in Haiti following the 2010 earthquake.
Following the 2010 Census, the 4th Congressional District was eliminated and Rep. Altmire was forced to run in the 12th Congressional District. He lost the Democratic primary to incumbent Mark Critz, and retired from public service. Altmire completed his term of service in 2013, and took a position as an executive with Florida Blue, Florida's Blue Cross Blue Shield company.
Previous Citation
Jason Altmire Congressional Papers, 2006-2012, AIS.2013.01, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jason Altmire, via Chief of Staff Michelle Dorothy, on November 15, 2012.
Access Restrictions
Material in Series IV. Constituent Communications is restricted for access due to privacy and confidentiality concerns. Access to this material may be granted after researcher request and consultation with ASC staff.
Existence and Location of Originals
The location of any original hardcopy files are unknown. The electronic records are only accessible through the "Digital Reading Room." To request access, please contact Archives & Special Collections through Ask-An-Archivist (https://www.library.pitt.edu/ask-archivist)
Scope and Content Notes
The collection includes official government publications, administrative files, travel files, constituent communications, correspondence, daily schedules, speeches, invitations, photographs, video, copies of legislation, memorabilia, talking points, congressional communications, committee hearing testimony, campaign materials, and press clippings. Areas of concentration within the collection include: military veterans, health care policy, small business, government reform, energy policy, education, labor, and transportation.
The series in the collection are arranged by subject alphabetically. There are two exceptions to the schema: audio-visual materials (moving image, photograph, and recorded audio), which are grouped alphabetically at the end of the collection, and Altmire's campaign files, which appear as a series also at the end of the collection. No materials were removed from the collection, but duplicates and special or redundant file formats were suppressed. The files themselves are named according to the following convention: YYYYMMDD_Title_Given.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This entire collection is comprised of 35,993 electronic files, consisting primarily of PDF, MP4, JPEG, and MP3 file formats.
ALL MATERIAL IN THIS COLLECTION IS ACCESSIBLE FROM ARCHIVES & SPECIAL COLLECTIONS "Digital Reading Room." RESEARCHERS WILL NEED TO REQUEST ACCESS BY CONTACTING THE ARCHIVES & SPECIAL COLLECTIONS BY SENDING A MESSAGE THROUGH Ask-An-Archivist (https://www.library.pitt.edu/ask-archivist).
Veterans -- Services for -- United States; Medical care -- United States; Legislators -- Pennsylvania -- Fourth Congressional District; Legislators -- United States; Congressional records; Education -- United States; Small business -- United States; Energy policy -- United States; Labor policy -- United States; Education and state -- United States; Medical policy -- United States; United States -- Politics and government -- 2001-2009; United States -- Politics and government -- 2009-; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Political campaigns -- Pennsylvania; Born digital; Correspondence; Speeches; Photographs; Sound recordings; Invitations; Moving images; Personal papers; Politics; Press releases; Elections -- Pennsylvania; United States. Congress. House; Altmire, Jason; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Education and the Workforce
- Administrative Files, 2006-2012; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains all administrative and managerial files generated by and for the Congressman's offices in Washington D.C. and in the PA-04 district. The series contains official House of Representatives administrative files, copies of the Congressman's daily schedule while in office, weekly reports for the Congressman's offices, staff lists and procedural guides, and a visitor log book for the year 2008. The files are arranged by subject alphabetically.
  - Daily Schedule, 2007-2012 (Folder 1)
  - DC Weekly Reports, 2007-2012 (Folder 2)
  - District Weekly Reports, 2009-2012 (Folder 3)
  - Policies and Procedures for House of Representatives, 2006-2011 (Folder 4)
  - Staff Administrative Files, 2012 (Folder 5)
  - Visitor Log Book, 2008 (Folder 6)
- Congressional Correspondence, 2006-2012; II.
  This series contains correspondence received by the Congressman during his tenure. Unlike his constituent communications, this correspondence is primarily a record of communication between the Congressman and non-constituents, including members of government at the local, state, and federal level, as well as foreign, diplomats, corporations, non-profit organizations, and supporters of the Congressman's elections campaigns. The files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Campaign Correspondence, 2007-2009 (Folder 7)
  - From Members of Congress, 2007-2012 (Folder 8)
  - Haiti Rescue Correspondence, 2010 (Folder 9)
  - Health Care Reform, 2009-2010 (Folder 10)
  - Letters of Congratulations, 2006-2010 (Folder 11)
  - Response Letters, 2007-2012 (Folder 12)
  - Various Correspondence, 2006-2012 (Folder 13)
- Congressional Delegation Files, 2007-2012; III.
  This series contains files and records of congressman Altmire's four overseas trips as a member of an official COngressional DELegation (CODEL). These files document travel and trips to Kuwait, Iraq, Qatar, Afghanistan, China, South Korea, the Czech Republic, Slovakia, Georgia, Djibouti, and Yemen. The series includes itineraries, briefing reports produced by the Congressional Research Service, maps, trip reports written by the Congressman, brochures, and American embassy documents. The series is organized by date and official destination. Please see Series XIV. Photographic Files for pictures taken during these trips.
  - CODEL to Iraq, August 2007 (Folder 14)
  - CODEL to Pakistan/Afghanistan, February 2008 (Folder 15)
  - CODEL to China/South Korea, July 2012 (Folder 16)
  - CODEL to Georgia/Slovakia, July 2012 (Folder 17)
- Constituent Communications, 2007-2012; IV.
  This series contains the district correspondence created or received by Congressman Altmire. It includes mailers, e-newsletters, copies of response letters to constitutent issues, and a sampling of letters received by his district and D.C. offices. This series also contains PDF copies of the Congressman's Facebook and Twitter pages. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Constituent Services Cards, 2007-2012 (Folder 18)
  - E-Newsletters, 2007-2012 (Folder 19)
  - Flyers, 2008-2011 (Folder 20)
  - Form Responses, 2007-2012 (Folder 21)
  - Mailers, 2007-2012 (Folder 22)
  - Sample Received Constituent Letters, 2007-2012 (Folder 23)
  - Social Media Accounts, 2011 (Folder 24)
  - Thank You Cards, 2007-2012 (Folder 25)
- Thank You Cards and Letters, 2007-2012; V.
  This series contains thank you cards received by the Congressman during his tenure. Unlike his constituent communications and Congressional correspondence, these cards and letters represent broader communication between the Congressman and local, regional, national, and international figures. These include fellow legislators, government officials, journalists, corporations, non-profit organizations, business leaders, and foreign diplomats. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Corporations, 2007-2012 (Folder 26)
  - Elected Officials, 2007-2012 (Folder 27)
  - Government Offices and Personnel, 2007-2012 (Folder 28)
  - Individuals, 2007-2008, 2010 (Folder 29)
  - Non-Profit Organizations, 2007-2012 (Folder 30)
- Invitations, 2007-2012; VI.
  This series contains invitations received by the Congressman to attend events or serve in positions within his district, as well as the District of Columbia and elsewhere. There are no materials to indicate which of the invitations were actually accepted. Due to the large volume of these invitations, the series is split into two subseries: district invitations and D.C. and out of district invitations, and arranged chronologically.
  - District Invitations, 2007-2012; 1.
    This subseries contains invitations to events within the PA-04 Congressional District received by the Congressman between 2007-2012. These invitations include meeting requests, awards ceremonies, parade invitations, community celebrations, and annuals meetings and galas for community organizations. The files are arranged chronologically by date of the event.
    - 2007 (Folder 31)
    - 2008 (Folder 32)
    - 2009 (Folder 33)
    - 2010 (Folder 34)
    - 2011 (Folder 35)
    - 2012 (Folder 36)
  - District of Columbia and Out-of-District Invitations, 2007-2012; 2.
    This subseries contains invitations to events within the District of Columbia and elsewhere, received by the Congressman between 2007-2012. These invitations include meeting requests, Congressional "meet and greets," official White House invitations, awards ceremonies, invitations to serve on non-profit boards, and others. The files are arranged chronologically by date of the event.
    - 2007 (Folder 37)
    - 2008 (Folder 38)
    - 2009 (Folder 39)
    - 2010 (Folder 40)
    - 2011 (Folder 41)
    - 2012 (Folder 42)
- Issue Files, 2007-2012; VII.
  This series contains records of the specific legislative issues and bills that the Congressman was involved in or sponsored during his Congressional tenure. These records include letters circulated by the Congressman to his colleagues, talking points for specific issues and events, policy and research materials utilized to support issues, and letters of support for specifc acts or bills from endorsing organizations. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - "Dear Colleague" Letters, 2007-2012 (Folder 43)
  - Economic Recovery, 2009-2010 (Folder 44)
  - Health Care Reform, 2009-2010 (Folder 45)
  - Higher Education Act, 2007-2008 (Folder 46)
  - Quality FIRST Act, 2008-2009 (Folder 47)
  - Reading First Program, 2007-2008 (Folder 48)
  - Sabo Post Office Renaming, 2012 (Folder 49)
  - Small Business Investment Act, 2007-2009 (Folder 50)
  - Small Reactors, 2010 (Folder 51)
  - Surface Transportation Bill, 2011 (Folder 52)
  - Talking Points, 2007-2012 (Folder 53)
  - Veterans and Reservists Small Business Act, 2007-2008 (Folder 54)
  - Veterans Guaranteed Bonus Act, 2007-2008 (Folder 55)
  - Yellow Ribbon Amendment, 2012 (Folder 56)
- Legislative Files, 2007-2012; VIII.
  This series contains the record of the Congressman's legislative activities and voting record during his tenure. The series includes memos, official tesimony, copies of legislation he introduced and co-sponsored, a listing of legislative accomplishments, Congressional letters he authored and/or signed on to, and his offical voting record prepared by the Clerk of the House of Representatives. The series is divided into subseries chronologically by Congressional session.
  - 110th Congress, 2007-2008; 1.
    This subseries contains the Congressman's legislative activities and voting record for the 110th Congress.
    - Briefing Memos (Folder 57)
    - Committee on Education and Labor- Statements for the Record (Folder 58)
    - Committee on Small Business- Statements for the Record (Folder 59)
    - Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure- Statements for the Record (Folder 60)
    - Co-Sponsored and Introduced Legislation (Folder 61)
    - Legislative Accomplishments (Folder 62)
    - Signed Letters (Folder 63)
    - Voting Record (Folder 64)
  - 111th Congress, 2009-2010; 2.
    This subseries contains the Congressman's legislative activities and voting record for the 111th Congress.
    - Briefing Memos (Folder 65)
    - Committee on Education and Labor- Statements for the Record (Folder 66)
    - Committee on Small Business- Statements for the Record (Folder 67)
    - Co-Sponsored and Introduced Legislation (Folder 68)
    - Legislative Accomplishments (Folder 69)
    - Signed Letters (Folder 70)
    - Voting Record (Folder 71)
  - 112th Congress, 2012-2013; 3.
    This series contains the Congressman's legislative activities and voting record for the 112th Congress.
    - Authored Provisions Signed into Law- All Congresses, 2007-2012 (Folder 72)
    - Briefing Memos (Folder 73)
    - Co-Sponsored and Introduced Legislation (Folder 74)
    - Legislative Accomplishments (Folder 75)
    - Signed Letters (Folder 76)
    - Voting Record (Folder 77)
- Personal Files, 2007-2012; IX.
  This series contains personal memorabilia and correspondence belonging to the Congressman. It includes birthday cards, holiday cards, Presidential speeches, programs for events in PA-04 and the District of Columbia, ticket stubs, and other scanned ephemera. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Birthday Cards, 2007-2012 (Folder 78)
  - Birthday Cards, undated (Folder 79)
  - Copies of Presidential Remarks, 2009-2011 (Folder 80)
  - D.C. Event Programs, 2008-2011 (Folder 81)
  - District Programs, 2009-2011 (Folder 82)
  - Holiday Cards, 2007-2012 (Folder 83)
  - Holiday Cards, undated (Folder 84)
  - September 11 Observance Events, 2008-2011 (Folder 85)
  - Ticket Stubs, 2007-2012 (Folder 86)
  - Various Ephemera, 2008-2012 (Folder 87)
- Press Files, 2002-2012; X.
  This series contains a record of the Congressman's press coverage both before and during his tenure in Congress. The series includes press clippings, monthly logs of his press coverage, op-eds authored by the Congressman, and official press releases from the Congressman's office. The series is arranged in subseries by subject.
  - Monthly Press, Radio, and Television Logs, 2008-2011; 1.
    This subseries contains monthly logs kept by the Congressman's office of all of his press mentions, including print, radio interviews, television mentions, and appearances. The logs record the date and time, news service/station, and subject of each broadcast/article. The actual press clippings are found in Subseries 3 of this series, while the radio and television clips are found in Series XV and XVI, respectively. These records are incomplete, as it appears the staff did not record this information for every month and year of the Congressman's tenure. The logs are arranged by year.
    - 2008 (Folder 88)
    - 2009 (Folder 89)
    - 2010 (Folder 90)
    - 2011 (Folder 91)
  - Op-Eds, 2007-2012; 2.
    This subseries contains op-eds authored by the Congressman during his tenure in Congress. The files are arranged alphabetically by issue/legislative subject.
    - Children's Health and Medicare Protection Act (CHAMP), August 14, 2007 (Folder 92)
    - Congressional Swearing-In Ceremony, January 9, 2007 (Folder 93)
    - Declaration of Independence, July 3, 2011 (Folder 94)
    - Hydraulic Fracturing in Marcellus Shale Region, undated (Folder 95)
    - Light Bulb "Ban" Controversy, undated (Folder 96)
    - Medical Device Equipment Tax, June 6, 2012 (Folder 97)
    - Voting No on Health Care Reform, November 20, 2009 (Folder 98)
  - Press Clippings, 2002-2012; 2007-2012; 3.
    This subseries contains clippings of press coverage the Congressman received, both locally and nationally, before and during his Congressional tenure. The bulk of the clippings cover his Congressional career, starting with the announcement of his candidacy in 2005 and running through the end of his Congressional term in 2012. These files compliment the legislative and correspondence series in the collection and cover the public perception of and reaction to the Congressman's activities in the House. The files are arranged by year.
    - 2002 (Folder 99)
    - 2003 (Folder 100)
    - 2004 (Folder 101)
    - 2005 (Folder 102)
    - 2006 (Folder 103)
    - 2007 (Folder 104)
    - 2008 (Folder 105)
    - 2009 (Folder 106)
    - 2010 (Folder 107)
    - 2011 (Folder 108)
    - 2012 (Folder 109)
  - Press Releases, 2007-2012; 4.
    This subseries contains press releases and public advisories produced by the Congressman's office. The files are arranged by the year.
    - 2007 (Folder 110)
    - 2008 (Folder 111)
    - 2009 (Folder 112)
    - 2010 (Folder 113)
    - Advisories, 2011 (Folder 114)
    - 2011 (Folder 115)
    - 2012 (Folder 116)
- Speech Files, 2007-2012; XI.
  This series contains the Congressman's personal copies of speeches he delivered on the House floor during his tenure in Congress. These documents display slight to significant differences from the Congressman's speeches as they are recorded in the official Congressional Record. The series is arranged by Congressional session, and includes speeches the Congressman wrote but are not recorded in the Congressional Record.
  - 110th Congress, 2007-2008 (Folder 117)
  - 111th Congress, 2009-2010 (Folder 118)
  - 112th Congress, 2011-2012 (Folder 119)
  - Additional Speeches, undated (Folder 120)
- State and District Files, 2007-2012; XII.
  This series contains records of the Congressman's activities in service to his constituents in the PA-04 district. Primarily, the series contains letters sent by the Congressman to various state and federal agencies to support funding requests from various businesses, municpalities, and organizations. The series also contains supporting materials, such as Congressional Research Service guides, district statistics, and agendas from workshops he held to support constituents. The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - 4th Congressional District Statistics, 2008-2012 (Folder 121)
  - Congressional Research Service Guides, 2011-2012 (Folder 122)
  - Federal Funding Resources, 2011-2012 (Folder 123)
  - Fire Department Grant Support Letters, 2008-2011 (Folder 124)
  - Health Care Grant Support Letters, 2008-2012 (Folder 125)
  - Law Enforcement Grant Support Letters, 2008-2011 (Folder 126)
  - Municipal and County Grant Support Letters, 2008-2012 (Folder 127)
  - Non-Profit and Faith-Based Organization Grant Support Letters, 2007-2012 (Folder 128)
  - Parks & Recreation Grant Support Letters, 2010-2012 (Folder 129)
  - School Program Grant Support Letters, 2008-2012 (Folder 130)
  - Small Business Grant Support Letters, 2008-2012 (Folder 131)
  - Workshop Agendas, 2010-2011 (Folder 132)
- Moving Image Files, 2007-2013; XIII.
  This series contains the complete record of the Congressman's television and recorded appareances during his Congressional tenure. The videos in this series include official House C-SPAN coverage, recorded committee hearings, speeches given at public events, public service announcements, commercials and consituent support videos for the PA-04 district, media appearances, and longer recorded interviews. The series is divided into subseries separating official video, media appearances, and other recordings.
  - C-SPAN Coverage, 2007-2013; 1.
    This subseries contains all appearances of the Congressman on the House's official C-SPAN channel during his tenure. These videos include normal legislative proceedings of the full chamber, committee hearings, and video of the Congressman serving as the Speaker Pro Tempore in House Speaker Nancy Pelosi's absence. The files are arranged chronologically.
    - 2007 (Folder 133)
    - 2008 (Folder 134)
    - 2009 (Folder 135)
    - 2010 (Folder 136)
    - 2011 (Folder 137)
    - 2012 (Folder 138)
    - 2013 (Folder 139)